Hello everyone, welcome. It's January
15th, 2026 and we're in active inference
model stream number 19.1 with Patrick
Kenny and Thomas Parr and Norsaget as
guests discussing active inference in
discrete state spaces from first
principles. Patrick has a presentation
and also we will hear from our guests
and read any questions from the live
chat. So Patrick to you for the
presentation and thank you. Go for it.
>> Uh thanks Daniel. Um so my title is
active inference in discrete state
spaces from first principles.
Now let me explain briefly why discrete
state spaces. It's because the
what I think is a natural formulation of
active inference is the path integral
formulation and this is very easy to get
to grips with in discrete state spaces
because you can do it with a hidden
markup model as the dynamic model. It's
um not so obvious what uh you can do in
continuous state spaces with uh
continuous time. If you want to do uh
the path integral formulation and uh
develop it to uh to the point where it
might actually be of some use in uh
practical applications
and when I say from first principles
that's a nod if you like to the free
energy principle I'm proposing that um
uh active inference the problems that
need to be addressed
can be tackled by standard um methods
that have been developed in machine
learning. in particular the mean field
approximation
uh without having to appeal to the um to
the free energy principle and uh I'll
explain that there are some limitations
that this discipline uh imposes but also
some uh advantages which uh which acrew
from um adhering to uh traditional well
understood methods that have been
developed uh in machine learning based
learning obviously.
So um I'll explain then the mean field
approximation
uh how that uh
addresses the fundamental problem in
active inference the um uh processing
the uh perception action cycle so that
um an agent can uh infer
its uh future actions from its past
history
and um essentially by uh predicting its
uh future sensations
and uh how this leads to an optimization
criterion. In fact, it's a KL divergence
criterion which is not quite the same as
expected free energy. It's very similar
but there is a subtle uh difference
which uh which I will dwell on a bit. uh
and I will explain that there are other
natural applications of the mean field
approximation in uh active inference
which um do not appeal to the um free
energy principle. In particular the uh
the problem of basian learning of HMM is
a direct application of the mean field
approximation.
uh also the problem of um of uh updating
beliefs about uh policies
uh that too is amanable to treatment by
the meanfield approximation
and then I'll conclude with u the pros
and cons of of doing things this way.
So
here's the the mean field approximation
in its um uh most compact form. You have
a target distribution which you want to
approximate
but uh is typically uh intractable in
the sense that the
well say that the the partition function
can't be uh evaluated. You can't
normalize it as a probability
distribution. That's the typical
scenario
and you want to approximate it by a
tractable distribution which is
traditionally denoted by Q and the
criterion is the uh divergence from Q to
P. This is the form of the divergence
which is
uh capable of being evaluated under
these assumptions that Q is tractable
and P is intractable.
And the uh the basic assumption is very
simple. You assume that uh that Q uh
factorizes in this way so that the state
space can be split up into streams which
are statistically independent
under the approximating distribution not
necessarily under the original
distribution.
And there's a very simple rule for um
uh estimating or calculating the factors
in this factorization for Q. It excuse
me it requires that you update these
factors asynchronously one at a time
according to this prescription.
Okay. You take the the log of the target
distribution.
you average out all of the um
components other than the component of
interest qx of n um by using the current
uh estimates of the factors and then you
renormalize the result by passing it
through a uh sigmoid function in order
to get a um a probability distribution.
So the things to note about this um
first is that the criterion the
divergence is guaranteed to decrease on
uh each iteration
and secondly that you don't actually
have any choice
in how the update formulas are to be
derived. They are determined by the form
of the generative model that you're
approximating P of X and the
factorization that you're going to
impose on the approximating
distribution. That's different from the
free energy principle. You don't have
any choice in how you're going to um do
the updating.
uh it's mo the mean field approximation
is mostly used in calculating sterior
distributions
and in that special case
uh the way you handle it is by uh
clamping
uh one of the um variable substreams to
the observed value. you're calculating
the posterior distribution of all of the
variables other than the v other than
the variable that has been observed. And
in the mean field approximation, you
simply clamp the um that component to
the observed value which I've denoted
here by x0 bar.
Now the main point I want to make in
this paper is that uh although the
uh meanfield approximation is
traditionally used in calculating
approximate posterior distributions
which of course is the problem of
perceptual in inference.
It can also be used to approximate
predictive distributions so that uh an
agent can use it to predict his future
sensations and thereby infer the uh
actions which he is going to embark on.
So um the
for this I need now to introduce some
more notation.
Uh the variable stream I assume is going
to be split between hidden variables and
observable variables. The hidden
variables I denote by S and the
observable variables by by O.
And the relationship between variation
of free energy and the mean field
approximation
is summarized by that uh boxed equation.
This is not one of the usual ways of uh
expressing variation free energy. It
turns out to be the one that's most
convenient for uh for my purposes.
If you uh impose the constraint on the
factorization that I just um described
in the last slide in this notation,
okay, where I'm distinguishing between
hidden and observable variables,
the variation free energy is just the KL
divergence between the target
distribution and the approximate
distribution where the approximate
distribution is required to satisfy this
constraint here.
So uh this uh this is not a one of the
usual ways of characterizing variation
of free energy but it's a simple um
calculation which is um
easy to to derive it's it's done in the
paper. I'm not going to go into the
details.
So, so this is how the mean field
approximation solves the problem of
perceptual inference where you have uh
the agent has uh recorded sensory
observations and wants to infer the
state of the world or the past history
of the world up to the up to the present
moment. And the problem I want to focus
on is how the mean fail approximation
can solve the problem of active
inference, which is to say how it can
produce appro approximate predictive
distributions for the future sensations
of of the agent.
So here's the um here's the picture.
Um I I'm assuming that uh the agent is
modeling its world by a hidden markup
model. Okay. So that all of the agents
knowledge about the world including the
repertoire of actions, the repertoire of
possible sequences at a time zero and
the prediction horizon uh extends to a
time capital t. All of the uh s
variables are hidden. Their values have
to be inferred.
But at a given time there will be a
history of past observations that uh
that have been recorded. So I've denoted
these by 01 up to to OT using the uh
white background.
and the future observations which have
to be predicted
uh I've used this hash hashing to uh
distinguish them. So all the hash nodes
indicate
um variables that have not yet been
observed or have to be predicted.
So um
let's see the problem of perceptual
inference is just a matter of
approximating
a posterior distribution
on the states up to the present moment
given the observations up to the present
moment. Whereas active inference is the
problem of it can be viewed as the
problem of
uh approximating the posterior
distribution
on the future states and future
observations given the observations up
to the present
and uh what I'm proposing in the paper
that uh both of these problems can be
solved in an integrated way by
minimizing a single divergence between
an approximating distribution Q and the
HMN P
uh where the um mean field approximation
uh implements the the mechanics.
the um constraints on on Q okay are
simply that okay so I'm using the
standard conventions here uh Roman T
little t is the present time the Greek
uh towel is any time in the past and the
future up to the planning uh horizon
which is capital T. So the uh we have a
standard uh factorization
where the constraints on the
factorization
are that um the observable variables
their values have already been observed
at the present time t and the future uh
observables are distributed according to
the emission probab probabilities of the
hidden markup model.
That's the only constraint that's
imposed on the factorization that feeds
into the the main field uh
approximation.
So um
assuming that the um that the hmm that
the state space is sufficiently small
that you can pre-ompile
the um the matrix of uh transition
probabilities.
You can work out the um the mean field
updates in a fairly straightforward way.
the the the mechanics are presented in
the paper. And if you're uh in the
situation of
this is the time index that refers to
any time in the past or the future. If
you're in the situation where that time
index is referring on to the past
so that you've already got an
observation history, then these are the
update formulas. And um I expect
everybody watching this video will
recognize that these are just standard
update formulas for minimizing variation
of free energy such as are presented in
the uh active inference textbook. The
only difference is that for uh a
technical reason that uh that I will
explain the uh
uh Q at uh time towel equal to zero is
uh not being updated. It's assumed to be
inherited from the uh agents uh prior uh
actions.
Um so this thing um would be I guess the
D matrix in the in the in the standard
convention but um there's a slight
departure from the um from the standard
treatment of time to equal to zero uh in
the paper which I will explain uh when I
come to it. Now this is the update
formula in the case where the Greek uh
letter towel the the time at that time
index is in the past
but and that solves the problem of
perceptual inference but for active
inference you need to predict the future
rather than retradict the past. So
there's another set of uh of update
equations
which uh is almost the same.
This uh this h here is the vector of
entropies of the emission uh
distributions in the hmm.
Okay, you can't actually you don't
actually have observations for future
times. you have to uh average over all
possibilities and what you get is just
the negative entropy. The um the only
difference between this and the previous
slide is that
uh for times in the past the uh
observation history is available.
Uh for times in the future you just have
to um excuse me for times in the future.
this one here uh you just have to
average over all possible futures and
you just end up substituting this uh
entropy uh vector in it in the place of
the observations in the past.
So these um these uh update formulas
both in the past and the future are
guaranteed to uh to decrease the
divergence between the approximating
distribution and the and the hidden
market model. So the basic posit here is
that if an agent models its world by a
hidden mark of model
and it wants to calculate a predictive
distribution for its future
observations, then the right way to
um evaluate the quality of the its
predictive distribution is to measure
its divergence from the HMM. The hmm is
what the agent would use if the state
space were sufficiently small to do uh
exact uh calculations. Of course, our uh
basic assumption is that the safe space
is so complicated that variational
methods are are needed. And the natural
approximation, at least to my way of
thinking, the natural criterion for
deciding how well a predictive
distribution
is fit for purpose is to compare it with
the HMM to calculate the divergence,
which excuse me, to calculate the HMM,
which holds
all of the agents knowledge about the
world that
inhabits.
Okay. To see then what all of this has
to do with um the free energy principle.
There's a
naturally if you look at the
constraints, it's obvious that there's
going to be uh a decomposition
in the divergence criterion, a
contribution from the past and a
contribution from the future. And you
can tease those out. The as far as the
past is concerned, the observable
variables are clamped to the actual
values of the observations. And as I
pointed out at the beginning, clamping
uh some of the variables
enables you to interpret the chaos
divergence as a variation of free
energy. That's the first component here.
the second component. Okay, when you
work it out, it's the divergence between
the um
the approximating distribution in the
future and the HMN in the future. But if
you look at the constraints that I
imposed, okay, I assumed that the
approximating distribution inherits
the emission probabilities
from the HMM. So when you're calculating
a divergence, the only possible scope
for a divergence between the uh
approximating distribution and the H&M
is in the state space. Okay, so the
joint divergence here simplifies
to a marginal divergence and that's this
second term here. So the basic claim
that I'm making in the paper is that
this thing is what is most natural to
look at in place of the uh future free
expected free energy for the purposes of
calculating predictive distributions.
Now, as I mentioned at the beginning,
there is in fact a very close
relationship between this and expected
free energy, but they're not quite the
same. So, I'll briefly explain what that
uh what that difference is.
So, here uh in this slide, I've just
reviewed the uh standard way of defining
expected free energy. Okay. Uh so what
we have is if we
assume that the
posterior distribution okay uh for the
future observations the posterior
distribution on states or state
sequences
is independent of the observation. This
is something that's done in formulating
expected free energy but it's obviously
not done in formulating variational free
energy.
Uh but uh it's has the advantage that
you get something that's uh easily
computationally tractable. Okay, you
start with this uh definition.
You do some fairly standard
uh manipulations and you get
a a marginal divergence which is just
like the thing I pointed to in the last
slide together with this uh ambiguity
term. Then you do some more fiddling
approximation
and you get the standard
uh expected free energy function or uh
consisting of the uh pragmatic value and
the mutual information or uh information
gain term. So that's the standard way of
doing things. If you do similar fiddling
with the um marginal divergence,
uh what you end up with is the uh you
get the uh pragmatic value again the
same one as here but instead of the
mutual information you end up with an
entropy term. This is uh can be viewed
as an entropy regularizer.
Optimizing this will encourage you to um
produce approximate distributions that
have uh high entropy rather than um uh
high mutual information between the um
hidden and observables. This I think is
a reasonable thing from a biological
point of view. If uh if an agent is um
in the business of inferring its future
actions,
then it uh does need to be uh careful
not to be overconfident about its uh its
future future predictions. It needs to
be able to look ahead but also to know
uh the limitations
the degree uh to which uh its future
predictions are to be trusted.
So that would be if you like a
biological rationale for having this uh
entropy term here.
Now um this here was um this assumption
is can be relaxed. Okay, it's possible
to uh evaluate an expected free energy
without making this assumption here. And
uh when you do that okay you um dropping
this assumption variation of free energy
if the future observations were
available you would calculate it this
way and expected free energy you would
then average over all possible future
observation sequences and you do a bit
of um algebraic manipulation and you
find again an an entropy term that um
relates
this generalized expected free energy to
the marginal divergence which uh I have
suggested is the most natural way most
natural criterion for predicting the
future. So the relationship between the
criterion I'm proposing and
um expected free energy
uh defined in this generalized way uh is
the only difference between them is an
entropy regularizer
that uh encourages approximate
distributions which are of high entropy.
So uh I think I can say that what I'm
proposing uh is very faithful to the
spirit of the free energy principle but
there is a subtle difference um that has
to do with this uh regularization.
Uh there are a few other points I could
cover but uh I'm not going to linger on
them. just um to show firstly that the
um standard
um basian method of learning HMM
parameters
is in fact although it may not usually
be presented this way is a direct
consequence of the mean field
approximation
which is just a general
procedure for approximating complex
joint distributions by simple factorized
distributions. So all you have to do in
any application is figure out what is
the joint distribution you're trying to
approximate and what is the
factorization that you're going to
impose on the approximating
distribution.
So to the joint distribution in the case
of um learning HMM you need a joint
distribution on
um the HMM parameters
and the hidden states and the uh
observations
which is you see this second term here
is just the HMM and this is the directly
prior on the HM parameters and then you
approximate it uh by imposing uh a
suitable factorization
and then you just turn the crank. Uh the
mean field approximation is just a
straightforward mechanical procedure
once you have set the thing up properly.
And what emerges in this case is just
the uh standard procedure for uh
estimating hmm parameters.
Uh one other application which is a bit
more technical but I explain it uh in
detail in the paper is how the uh mean
field approximation applies to the uh
problem of updating beliefs
uh about uh policies.
Um this uh assuming that you have a
prior distribution of policies that
would uh I think typically be denoted by
a vector E in in the in the active
inference literature and you have
observations in the past and you have a
probability distribution. Well, you want
to calculate a posterior distribution
given the observations in the past. Um
you can do it just by uh figuring out
exactly what is the joint distribution
of the hidden variables that you're
going to approximate. What are the uh
conditions that you impose on the
factorization in order to make the mean
field updates computationally tractable.
And you end up with a formula which is
very similar to uh an equation in the
active inference uh textbook with the
difference that what plays the role of
expected free energy is this thing this
contribution of the future to the kale
divergence.
Okay. And it's not an expected
re-energy.
So uh that's a bit too technical to uh
dwell on any further. I'll just say that
anyone who's interested can find it in
the paper.
So I can now uh conclude
the um
so the the mean field approximation can
be brought to bear on all of the basic
problems in the uh in active inference.
Okay. The three that we looked at was
how to infer how an agent can infer a
predictive distribution
on its future sensory
observations
from uh an observation history
data that has been collected in the
past. Um how um the method approximation
applies to the problem of basian
learning of hmms. how it um enables you
to
uh update beliefs about policies in a a
um principled way.
The
limitations of the method are that the
objective function has to be a kale
divergence.
the the function that you're trying to
optimize.
This uh presents no problem in uh the
case of perceptual inference. Okay,
because the although it's not usually
done, variation of free energy can be
expressed directly as a kale divergence.
However, this is not true of expected
free energy. expected free energy. No
matter how you define it, it's not a
scale divergence, but you can manipulate
it uh by adding in an entropy
regularizer so that you actually do get
a GL divergence
so that the objective function is
amanable to the mean field
approximation.
And the critical point I think is that
the uh update formulas for the mean and
field approximation are determined. You
don't have any choice. They're
determined by the joint distribution of
the variables you are uh which are
germanine to the situation that you're
working in and the constraints that are
imposed by the factorization. Once those
have been written down, everything else
was mechanical. But you don't have any
choice in writing down the update
formulas. Everything is governed by the
generative model. That's my sort of
basic assumption that an agent
that's navigating a discrete state space
using a uh HMM to encode all of its
knowledge about its world and that
governs the um the updates.
The major advantage I think is that
there is a convergence guarantee. the uh
if you uh have implemented things
properly, the KL divergence is
guaranteed to decrease on every belief
update.
And as far as I know, there are no
convergence guarantees for the free
energy principle.
So that concludes my talk. Um,
I guess I'll continue to um to share the
screen in case there are any questions
about um
uh any formulas or anything.
>> Thank you. Great. All right. Yes, leave
the slides up,
Thomas, if you would like to make any
first comments or I can just ask some
preliminary questions. And meanwhile,
people who are watching live can write
in the chat. If you'd like to go first
though, Thomas, go for it.
>> I'd suggest we do it that way actually,
Daniel, because I'm interested in what
people ask and then we can sort of
discuss some of those points afterwards
if that's okay.
>> Great. Okay. So, uh, people watching
live can write in the chat. Let me just
ask a few clarifying questions while
people are writing, Patrick.
So in the first introduction of the VFE,
>> if you could go back to that slide on I
think decomposing the divergence.
>> Oh, the the slide, excuse me, the slide
entitled decomposing the divergence
>> a little bit back
>> there. Okay.
>> Uh when I mentioned the variation of
free energy was here.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Thank you. Here. So
here you have the VF defined by only the
KL divergence between the joint
distribution of the Q approximation and
the P. In equation 2.5 of the 2022
textbook in the third line, there's a
divergence and an evidence term. So have
you just only focused on the KL
divergence aspect or is is there a
different role for how you've derived?
>> This this is literally the same as the
um standard presentation. There are
actually three standard presentations of
the variational free energy and what I'm
saying is that this one is uh exactly
the same just written in a different way
is it it actually requires a little bit
of pencil and paper calculation to see
that but uh it's it's in the paper.
>> Okay. Perhaps just to make to make that
clear. So you know that that the um kale
divergence here can be separated out
into a difference between um an entropy
and an energylike term just as the the
variational free energy would be and the
the entropy term comes from the first
the cq bit here. Now if you were to
separate out the but because the entropy
is a log term you can separate out into
a sum of the entropy of Q of S and the
the um delta distribution here. So the
entropy of the delta distribution is
going to be zero by definition. So will
vanish which leaves you with just the Q
of S bit. So it's exactly the same.
>> Okay. It is obvious to you then. Good.
It Yeah. Good.
>> Okay. So it wasn't it wasn't obvious to
me. I have to actually
uh if you look at the paper I I derived
it but uh in a more securious um way.
>> Yeah those those different
decompositions of the VFE in equation
2.5 and the EF which what my next
question will sort of be about. It's
very fascinating these kind of rings of
compatible
isomorphic or transformable equations
that all highlight different aspects.
And when it comes to the computational
implementations, sometimes certain
representations have different
computational uh availabilities or
resource needs depending on on state uh
space size and all of that.
>> So just
>> indeed.
>> Yeah. No, I would just say that for my
purposes, okay, it was essential to cast
the variation free energy as a single
scale divergence and nothing else
because that um that's what the mean
field approximation
uh is tailored to optimizing. So it just
reinforces your point. There are many
different ways of writing
uh these functionals which are u more or
less suitable depending on the um
context that you're working under.
>> Great. And then just one kind of similar
clarifying question about the
>> EF
>> that was a few slides later.
>> Okay. So just
>> so I had a couple of um
here perhaps or
>> or here.
>> Yeah,
>> this was the preamble to the um
developing the relationship between this
divergence criterion and the
>> but the um
>> yes go. Yeah. So, so just on on here
sort of conventionally the EF is modeled
as a sort of tree search unrolling of
conditional action sequences over the
policy time horizon and the consequences
of the the transition matrix slice
constituting the B tensor. So ho how
does the mean field or your formalism
here deal with the conditional effects
of different actions?
How can we average over expected
observations in a way that at least here
though I see later the pi variable and
the action conditionality comes into
play here I was a little surprised to
see this as a sort of temporal unfolding
Gaussian blur over observations that
doesn't immediately seem to condition
upon action selection.
>> Okay. Uh good question. the um in fact
it's it's really comes at the at the
heart of the matter for for this uh for
this paper. My um assumption is that the
uh agent encodes all of its knowledge
about its worm in a richly structured
hidden market model. So the the type of
model that I have in mind is the uh the
sort of model in the pixel what is it
called planning from pixels paper the
the one which uh gariston has called the
reormalization
uh the renormalization group model I I
forget exactly what his terminology is
but where where you have a a
hierarchical structure Okay. Where the
uh actions and policies
can be folded into the uh into the way
that the HMM states are defined.
Okay. So there's there's you actually
although the expect the the free energy
principle is
usually presented as a way of um
of uh making inferences about actions
which are currently underway or are yet
to be performed. That way of presenting
things uh hinges on a hard distinction
between
actions and uh and states. But if you
look at the sort of hierarchical uh
structure in the
um the um what's that paper called?
Planning from pixels. I I forget what
>> pixels to planning.
>> Pixels to planning. If you look at that
hierarchical structure where actions are
just transition probabilities on states,
okay, and the state structure then is
redefined so as to uh incorporate paths
and states into a similar into a single
structure. So you no longer actually
have to talk explicitly
about actions. Okay? everything can be
um formulated as inference in terms of a
richly structured uh hidden market
model. Well, that that's the perspective
that I'm taking in the paper that uh a
sufficiently richly structured model
encodes
all of the agents knowledge about the
world, its repertoire of actions, its
repertoire of
uh policies and it enables the agent to
do the um path integral calculations.
or um in order to make its uh
predictions.
>> Thomas, do you want to add any comments
to that or I can read two of the
questions in the chat?
>> Um I I think I'll have more comments on
and questions about this slide later,
but let's should we do the questions
first and then we can come back to that
if that's okay.
>> Great. All right. Alexander Sabine in
the chat wrote, "Is there any sense in
which active inference tracks the
cumulative cost of these KL updates over
the long time horizon?"
>> Well, the KL divergence here is not the
divergence from one static distribution
to another.
The the Q uh the approximating
distribution is approximating a hmm.
So both the Q distribution and the P
distribution are dynamic models.
So it's sort of it's built into the KO
divergence as long as you recognize that
it's the divergence from one dynamic
model to another rather than the
divergence from one static distribution
to another static distribution.
>> Thank you. And that to me at least sort
of rhymes with Rand Wei's work on
reinforcement learning and active
inference where the pragmatic value is
reflected by a MDP and then there's a
partially observable element which
contributes an epistemic uncertainty and
it's that double superposition of the
the pragmatic preference constraint
oriented and then the sheer entropic
uncertainty which together in a joint
functional make it active inference.
or indeed if I sorry but with it reminds
me of something I I I really should have
mentioned that there there is this uh
paper by um Hafner
uh whose title if I remember correctly
is
um is it action
and perception as divergence
minimization something like have which
uh is sort of unifies um many many
different uh algorithms in um uh
reinforcement learning under that single
umbrella of divergence minimization
and uh this too fits under that uh
umbrella as long as you understand that
the divergence that I'm talking about
here is a divergence between two uh
dynamic models. Okay. Rather than a
divergence between two uh static
distributions.
>> Great. Okay. And then second question in
the chat from Bert Burkers wrote, "Could
you explain H and the update rules in
more detail?"
>> Well, there um
there's a sort of
Sorry, just a sec. Um the
there is this um general perfectly
general mean field approximation which
can be used to
uh approximate any probability
distribution by a suitably factorized
approximate distribution on the same
variables. you simply by fiat impose
statistical uh independence assumptions
between the variables. That's what this
factorization
means. And um you try to find the
uh distribution that best approximates
the distribution you started with in the
sense of K's divergence subject to these
statistical independence constraints.
And that's a that's a universal
um mechanism.
And all I've done in this paper is apply
that to uh in the case of hidden markup
models. Okay, where um the distribution
is not a static distribution but a
distribution that unfolds over time. And
the approximation,
the constraints on the approximation are
that well the mean field constraint
which says that the uh variables at uh
different times are statistically
independent in the approximation. That's
just factorization.
And the other constraint is that if you
have an observation history at your
disposal, you clamp the observable
variables to those observed values in
the past. Okay? In the future, the
future is wide open. You just use the uh
emission probabilities from the HMM. And
then once you impose that, everything is
in principle mechanical. the uh the
update formulas
uh are just a matter of turning the
crank. Uh I've I've written them out in
detail in the paper that uh accompanies
this uh this presentation.
Uh it's no surprise that in respect of
times in the past, the update formulas
are just going to look like the standard
uh variation free energy updates.
and the
um updates in the future look uh very
very similar there. There's really not
that much uh difference between them.
>> Can I on that one?
>> Yeah, Thomas please.
So in so the the way in which the
updates from a mean field approximation
are obtained is that or one way in which
one can find those formula is that if
one takes the gradient of the kale
divergence or the functional derivatives
and finds the minima uh that then um the
minima is what you end up with there is
the the update. So they are the fixed
points uh so or the minima of that
objective function. Now I was puzzled by
the hes here as well. And the reason I
was a bit puzzled is because the kale
divergence you've written down here
with the factorization for future states
should essentially and you show this on
a later slide should cancel out both of
the O's because you will both the Q of S
given S and O and the P of S and O.
You'll be able to factoriize out a P of
O given S from both of those. And
because the kale divergence deals with
the difference between uh two log of
probabilities, those all completely
cancel out. And as you show in one of
the later slides, this kale divergence
is exactly equivalent to Q of S P of S
with no O's involved in it at all.
>> That's right.
>> So for the to end up with the um
emission probabilities in the um in the
update formula seems to me inexplicable.
Okay,
>> because they should cancel out and then
once one takes the the derivatives and
finds them in the kale divergence, they
shouldn't be there because they're not
in the kale divergence to begin with.
>> I I I agree they're not in the kale
divergence, but the aim of the
um of the mean field approximation is to
minimize the scale of diversions. Okay.
What you want what you want to do is
update the
um uh um factors. Okay. So as to arrive
at at least a local minimum of the kale
diversions. And for that uh you do need
to take into account the fact that the
um emission probabilities the the state
the states in the HMN
are um as they say heteroscadastic
they they have different um entropies.
If the if all the entropies were the
same, okay, what would happen is that
the hes would effectively drop out
because
uh what the what's going on here is that
to get these factors, you pass the right
hand side through a uh sigmoid function.
Okay? And if the all of the components
of this vector H were the same, if all
of the HM states had the same entropies,
then indeed the um the H's would
disappear. They would not play any role.
Um does that
>> I'm not trying to follow where you got
the hes from in the first place.
>> Okay. Okay. It's simply the um the it's
a vector having one component for each
state in the hidden market model
and the value of that component is the
entropy of the emission probability
distribution for that state.
>> Yes. So if you just look if you just if
you just look here I think you might see
what I'm getting at.
>> Sorry. Do you mind if I just clarify by
probability you you mean the probability
of B of O given S which
stand to be emission probability as
well. That's right. What I'm saying is
that that emission probability doesn't
exist in the kale divergence because it
cancels out.
>> I agree. I I agree it doesn't. But the
um the mean field approximation and this
is just a mechanical uh um derivation
okay does require that you take account
of the entropies of the HMM states in
updating the making predictions for the
future because obviously
uh the visiting uh visiting states with
uh with high entropy
is going to have an effect on the value
of the KL diversions that you that you
are optimizing. If I could just point to
one thing which I think might actually
clear up the confusion.
uh if you look in the what's going on
here this a matrix is the what I'm
calling the emission probabilities okay
so this is how the emission
probabilities
enter into the
standard variational free energy updates
right more or less taken from the tech
from the textbook I mean I I try to
align the notation with the uh with the
text file. Okay, that's in respect of
observations in the past.
Now in respect of
uh observations that have yet to be
collected okay what becomes of this term
okay is just the expected value the
conditional expectation of the
observation given the state or the log
of the um probability given the state
and that's how the entropy emerges.
in in this uh when you're predicting the
future.
>> Okay, I don't want to spend too long on
this point, but I I think you know for
me that that's not entirely clear still
and I I appreciate that the emission
probabilities appear in the previous
version.
Oh, sorry. In in relation to past states
and that's absolutely the case because
the kale divergence in relation to past
states is a functional of the emission
probabilities. If the kale divergence of
the future states is not a functional of
the emission probabilities
then in in finding its minimum if that
if that is what we doing to derive what
we're describing as the mean field
updates then the the minimum is
invariant to the emission probabilities
if you see what I mean I I I sort of
appreciate the the sort of formal
similarity
um but it feels like that probably the
issue comes as to how you're defining
your mean field updates and where they
come from and if they come from
minimization of the kale divergence they
can only depend upon things that are in
the kale divergence.
uh the kale divergence simp okay
I think the only answer I can give you
at this point okay given that we're sort
of going around in circles is that the
derivation of this is a simple
mechanical consequence of the mean field
uh update formulas and if you look at
the paper you find that I I stuff these
out in painful detail in uh in an
appendix because I didn't expect that
anyone would actually want to uh grapple
with them. But since it appears that
that you might want to do so, do by all
means and if it's still uh unclear, I
can straighten it out.
>> Let's leave that point there then, shall
we? as going around in circles. Daniel,
are there further questions or or either
from you or the chat
>> here? I was just wondering about the
shape of these. If H is already
vectorzed,
then we're calculating ln Q
kind of going laterally through time.
But then
I just don't see how I I like I I also
will will like to think more about it.
It seems like one of the key moves is to
make action of
um make of comparable kind
exter so-called external or internal
causal forces so that one's own actions
are part of the latent states.
So all causal unfoldings in the future
can be treated
in a common setting.
And then the question that arises to me
is where does the mean field
approximation
have
where where does that approximation and
a KL updating
lead to model adequacy?
Because even if retradiction and
prediction updating are guaranteed to
decrease
through the divergence,
is there any way to diagnose
our absolute adequacy
or do we need another kind of benchmark
otherwise the KL divergence convex
optimization
may not reflect destruct because it's
conditioned upon the
factorization of the generative model.
It may have limited applicability in
practice even if it has well
well-behaved
update rules.
>> Yeah. My my assumption the the basic
assumption perhaps I didn't make it
clear um sufficiently is that the
uh agents all of the agents knowledge of
the world can be encoded in a s in a hmm
of sufficiently rich structure
and if that is given then the natural
criterion
for uh an agent calculating predictive
distributions
is just the degree to which the
predictive distributions differ from the
predictions that would be made by the
HMM and that is encapsulated in the
divergence.
So the in the way that I am thinking of
things the generative model takes center
stage and that's not the way that the
free energy principle is usually
presented and I think the reason for
that is that
in the um original continuous state
space continuous time formulation of the
free energy principle
the um generative model was sort of a
stub the there was no uh obvious
candidate some sort of stochcastic
differential equation
was to play the role of the generative
model.
Whereas in the uh discrete state space
uh setup there is an obvious well
understood
uh generative model to use namely a
discrete HM
at least a discrete state space hmm and
if you put that in the center then
and you say that that is going to rule
over everything
Then the tail divergence
I think becomes the natural criteria for
evaluating the quality of predictive
distributions. How well do the
predictions approximate
the predictions that would be made by
exact calculations
with the H&M?
Yes,
Thomas, if you have any questions or I'm
curious how this lands or how you see
this in light of the high road and low
road approach that structures the 2022
textbook.
>> Yes. Um I mean that there's a lot that
that we could talk about here and um I
guess first of all I should say you know
thank you Patrick for for such an
engaging presentation.
>> Thank you. It was my pleasure to talk to
you about this.
I I think um you know it was a really
sort of clear and wellresented um
introduction to uh first of all use of
meanfield methods in um in basin
inference but formulated in terms of
kale divergence minimization
and I think also in terms of that notion
of of prediction and inference about
states that have yet to happen and and
we yet have yet to have data about.
Um and I think it's really interesting
thinking about the relationship between
that and expected free energy and and a
number of other things. Um there are a
few there there are one or two points in
fact one of them we've spoken about
already another one we'll come on to
that that I would take a little bit of
issue with in terms of the technical
aspects but some of the other points are
more a matter of
of being completely valid in and I
completely endorse what you say about
the the right sort of predictive
distribution is effectively the
distribution that aligns with the prior.
I completely endorse what you say that
the generative model is the thing that
should always be center stage and should
be the thing that uh that determines
behavior of any sort and I I I think
that's at the heart of the active
inference approach. Um uh and um
apologies if we weren't clear on that in
other in other areas. Um so I suppose
first question I have really is what is
going to be most useful for you? What
what what did you want to get out of
sort of initially contacting me about
this paper and what did you want to get
out of writing it? I suppose
>> well it started off reading your book. I
I I h I had a um I happen to have a a
background in in basian methods.
uh um I'm retired but I I used to be a
research engineer in in specifically um
speech recognition and speaker
recognition and um that was my hobby uh
developing basing methods to do that. Um
I saw basing methods pretty much blown
completely out of the water with the uh
uh you know with the deep learning uh uh
success you know the transformer and so
forth with one exception which was the
uh the um active inference uh community.
So I made it my business to um to read
the book and and had a lot of trouble
with it and ended up rethinking it uh in
the light of my previous experience with
uh with the mean field approximation.
this it's something that I happen to
have used all the time because of the
guaranteed uh convergence
um that's that's built in so that you
have a way of debugging uh complex
variational algorithms.
You just check that on every belief
update the um
uh often as the divergence criterion
uh decreases and as far as I can see
there is no such uh guarantee available
for the free energy principle. Um it's
plausible that uh that it should that
the belief updates should uh decrease
the optimization the optimization
criteria but I I I don't see any way
towards a convergence any sort of
convergence guarantee for the free
energy principle.
>> That's a really interesting point and
perhaps that's a an interesting um place
to start. So I suppose from some aspects
there is the the sort of exactly the
same guarantees as you have for the mean
field approach you've described in that
the variational energy is exactly the
kale divergence you've talked about and
uh the fixed points of the kale
divergence are also going to be the
fixed points of the corresponding
variational free energy. Um so in that
sense any guarantees that hold for one
also hold for the other. Um
>> could I just interrupt there and say
that um expected free energy and
variation of free energy
>> uh two different things
>> they're two different things
>> absolutely
>> go ahead
what the one the one is the kale
diversions and the other cannot be
expressed diversions
>> absolutely right
>> okay yeah
>> absolutely right now that's an
interesting point in itself and um and
again what there's A lot we could talk
about here and and we may perhaps come
back to that. Um the point about
convergence though so convergence for
the variational free energy and for
inference under that as you say is as
guaranteed as it is under any other
meanfield kale divergence minimization.
Um you said a few times that that there
is only one way of of uh using the mean
field approach. Uh and perhaps that's
true under under some definitions and
conventions. Uh we would often use it in
in the sense of it is this
factorization. These are the fixed
points we want to reach. But actually
you often we would use a gradient
descent process as an alternative. I
mean the fixed point iteration you
describe is absolutely valid. Um but
sometimes you can also particularly if
you're trying to model biological
systems express these things.
>> Yeah, absolutely. If you if you have
continuous emission distributions,
you're almost certainly going to have to
do gradient descent rather than the
coordinate ascent which um happens to be
so simple.
I'm sorry. or if you're doing inference
in continuous time as well. I mean so
the probabilities that indeed I
I made a sort of blanket
assumption in the paper that I was just
going to talk about discrete
distributions and discrete time and in
that case the why not use the coordinate
ascent rather than the uh gradient
descent because it's so straightforward.
>> Absolutely. No, it's it's a perfectly
valid way of doing it and and often
faster. Um but uh but it's worth saying
that even if you're using a model based
upon uh discrete categorical random
variables, the parameters of the
distributions describing those are still
continuous variables. And so uh you can
just as easily perform a continuous
coordinate descent. And there may be
differences between the times that are
being described by the model and the
time over which you're doing the
inference um within each of those steps.
So you know that that becomes much more
when you look at biological
>> well of course it's also true for
coordinate descent or the other one the
the
what's
the performance is critically dependent
on the starting point. you're only ever
driving towards a local minimum of the
of the optimand. So, um you're never
you're never going to find a perfect
solution to the uh to the problem and
the step size may indeed uh affect the
outcome of the um optimization.
>> Yes. And but then just to come back to
your point about convergence and
expected free energy and I suppose that
the question is do you think that
biological behavior and cognition and
exploration and decision-m is
convergent? Isn't some would argue that
there isn't open-endedness to the way in
which we behave that it actually doesn't
>> clearly the the functioning of the brain
is riddled with um closures and and
evolutionary hangovers and so on and
trying to reverse engineer that is sort
of
pretty well n a hopeless task. I I
um I mean to to exactly uh map onto
uh biological function seems to me to be
too ambitious.
But the the um I'm really looking at
this as an engineering problem. that
happens to be my I mean a very
um
unusual challenging engineering problem
to actually simulate the behavior of
biological
uh systems or or subsystems but um I I I
I really don't know enough to say
whether
incilico algorithms could actually
translate to too to wet where uh it's
really beyond my um um outside of my
wheelhouse altogether.
>> Well, I suppose the analogy I'm I'm sort
of implicitly drawing is that for a
biological creature, the only real fixed
point they will reach is death.
>> And
in the long run, we will
>> Yes. No, it didn't
to answer to answer the question you
asked about why why I got into this was
was I I I really thought this was
tremendously clever idea of that of of
uh extending you know the analogy
between variational
inference, thermodynamics
uh perception into into action because
you get so much more if you can make
that um that leap
uh which is basically the transition
from variation free energy to expected
free energy and that's what u set me on
this uh
on on this quest to initially just to
see if I could understand
uh expect free energy and I had so much
trouble with that that I found it easier
to um to work things out for myself. And
this is this is what I came up with. I
mean, I I don't have any real stake in
the um in the future of this. I I I'm no
longer at a stage in my life where I
maintain a CV or willing to pay for page
charges to uh to publish this sort of
thing. It's just the um a hobby that I
>> Well, okay. I mean, I think that's
useful in terms of, you know, this is an
exercise in exploration and curiosity,
which I think is is also something
that's worth coming back to. um the so
but but you've sort of very nicely
introduced this question of how do we go
from this idea of variational free
energy and and the like to the idea of
expected free energy or if we're not
going to do that what's what's the
alternative way of formulating it and
actually one of the things I found quite
interesting is that um that what you've
described is actually very very closely
related to the way in which um sort of
the the continuous state space
formulations of active inference have
typically worked
where it is all about I have some
generative model under which I'm making
some predictions a short way into the
future and taking actions to fulfill
those predictions. Um and that is that
is precisely the sort of reflexive like
actions to fulfill those predictions uh
that the the um the continuous states
those models have typically used and
actually those don't tend to appeal to
expected free energy. That's bit
something that's much easier and much
more tractable to to relate to um the
the the question of discrete state space
models as you spoke about before the
idea that actually if you can turn a
path integral into a sum over time it
becomes much more straightforward to
evaluate those alternative paths and uh
and the temporal aspect of it. Um the
way it's typically or or the way one
typically addresses paths and
predictions into the future in the
context of continuous states space
models is to make use of generalized
coordinates of motion which are
effectively a way of writing down a
Taylor series like approximation of a
local trajectory. And in
>> Could I ask you a question about about
that? It seems to me that that doesn't
uh take into account the the random
fluctuations that are in the Livang
equation. you you have the epsilon term
or whatever you call it. If you simply
take a tailaylor series expansion um
about the state at a given time, you're
not taking account of the
um the random shocks that the um that
the environment is going to
um
uh inject. So it seems to me to be too
cheap a way of trying to get from a
dynamic
setup to a static setup.
If you if you if you represent
everything by generalized coordinates,
you you simply got a static
distribution.
Well, you assuming you don't update them
as you go and and
>> Yeah, but but that's that's expos the
the the the update if the if the shock
comes in but you're not able to
anticipate the effect of those uh random
shocks if you're use at least this is my
naive reading of the continuous state
space and I tried to um I tried to make
clear in the paper that at least from my
point of view the right way to
straighten out the conceptual issues in
active inference is to start with the
discrete state space simply because
everything is so much more
straightforward and tractable.
>> Yes, I mean to try and answer your
question but as you say let's stick to
the discrete state space on the whole
here because that's the subject of your
presentation. Um to to answer your
question as to how you deal with the
random fluctuations,
if you have a distribution over both
over each element of your generalized
coordinates of motion over each of those
coordinates, then that will tell you how
how confident you are about where you
will be at different in time. And so the
effect of the random fluctuations comes
in through the the the variance of each
coordinate in turn, which means that the
further you get away from the current
point, the greater the uncertainty grows
in both directions.
And you know, for that reason, there's
actually a finite number of generalized
coordinates that are typically useful to
to employ in a generative model because
beyond a certain point, they add no more
confidence to the the the um the
distribution side. Um, and there's lots
of really interesting things one can do
looking at the the co-variance between
coordinates as well in the context of of
um smooth noise processes and and
correlated noise processes.
>> So it's a fascinating area but but as
you say let's stay away from that one
for now otherwise we'll end up put down
there a very interesting
um
>> and and you know in terms of what you've
you've set out I do I I do sort of
completely agree with you that that what
you're describing is the right way of
deriving predictions.
about what's going to happen next. And
in fact, exactly what one would get if
if one um included in a a standard
variational free energy future
observations as uh as if they were
hidden states. One would end up with
exactly the same updates. Again, I'm not
completely sure about these hes, but
we'll we'll leave that one. Mhm.
>> Um but now the the sort of discussion
about
divergences and you know some of the
papers you mentioned some of which I've
been involved in some of which I haven't
um the sort of action and perceptionist
divergence minimization
then I think in the paper you mentioned
Baron Le's paper wz the expected free
energy um you know we in a way one of
the reasons that this is so interesting
or one of the signs that this is so
interesting is that these are issues
that get revisited every every so often
>> and you know I remember having
conversations like this nearly 10 years
ago now
>> sure
>> the same sort of arguments and same sort
of discussions and I think I mentioned
to you in an email it's almost a right
of passage if of people as they start
>> world
>> um and and you know it's it's telling
that this is something that captures
people's um approach and I think it
people's attention and it's one of the
really interesting things that to some
extent I think is still unsolved in
active inference is why is it that
something like the expected free energy
works as well as it does? Why does it
capture as as many things as it does?
What's the relationship between it and
why does it look so similar to something
like the the free energy the variation
of free energy without actually being
the same sort of quantity in itself
without being directly derable from it
on that point while we're there the
other one point that I I I disagreed
with um in terms of what we've actually
said was there was a slide where you you
defined the expected for energy Daniel
went to that slide earlier on
>> as I find that I find that just
>> Yeah, that would be great.
>> This this is the this I presented as the
conventional treatment of expected free
energy and this as
>> what I'm proposing
your conventional treatment.
>> Okay.
So the point I wanted to make for for
anyone who who's not used to this is
that this is not the conventional
treatment. So the the line here that
says EF equals the expectation of VF is
not the conventional treatment. Um and
um I I think there probably are some
papers where something like this
appears. It certainly doesn't appear in
the book. Um and
actually has been a point of confusion
for quite a long time. And probably part
of this is um is that we shouldn't have
referred to it as an expected free
energy because it is not the expectation
of variational free energy.
>> Okay. Well, just in in my defense, I I
um I have spent a lot of time puzzling
over this um thing here.
>> Okay. And I wrote this down as what
appears to me to be the simplest route
to arriving at that and and stuck this
in as a flag. I mean the red color as a
flag to uh indicate that um there's some
threatening going on.
>> Yes,
>> that's an important point though Thomas.
So thank you indeed. There's been the
whole EF free energy of the expected
future expectation of variational free
energy and that was an important point.
>> Yes. By the way, Daniel, I should say do
interrupt me if I'm talking too much or
if there are other questions coming
through. Um assuming that there aren't
at the moment. Um I think you know we we
we we sort of come to one of the key
points here which is what what is the
expected free energy there to do?
Um and
where does it come from and where it
comes from is a complex question and I
think in many ways the way in which this
question has been approached has now
almost turned on its head that you know
this functional form appears to capture
a lot of interesting behavior.
remind me if I don't come back to it.
The other point we we should talk about
is um kinds of behavior that might be
captured by an expected free energy but
would not be captured by the formulation
you have here because I think that's
another really interesting and important
point to come back to. But in terms of
the motivation for it, I think that
there seem to be a lot of behaviors that
are really well captured by it. And it's
fascinating that they are captured by
something that has such a similar
functional form to the variation of
brain energy. Um and the reasons for
that I think are are to to many in many
ways still under investigation
and the way in which that's being
addressed now particularly in a number
of the papers that have looked at the
kind of underlying physics of um of the
free energy principle almost turn the
question round and say given this seems
to be such a good description of a
system what sort of minimal properties
of a dynamical system what sort of
conditional dependency structures in the
system itself have to be satisfied
before this emerges as a natural
formulation.
>> Well, I I I would um um
if I was pursuing that line of
investigation, okay, I would ask uh what
sort of generative model leads naturally
to this particular uh update formula? Is
there some way of defining a generative
model such that the mean field
approximation or something similar
actually enables you to derive this?
And I think the answer to that is is
that actually the way most of these
models are derive or defined is that the
expected free energy is not an objective
function in the classical sense. It is
part of one of the priors. It it it is
the way in which a prior over what I'm
going to do next is defined. And that's
the thing that's not present really in
in in in the formulation even here. I I
I try I did I did try to um satisfy that
objection by by deriving
uh this um this update formula for
policies
in the framework that um that I
developed. Um the the office I
anticipated that
um this was going to be an objection and
wrote this section in anticipation of
that. Whether you're satisfied with it
or not, I I I don't know. But I I I I
started I mean the the the where I
really stumbled trying to understand
free energy was or expected free energy
was how this equation your your B9 this
is my analog of it okay could be derived
from this update formula I mean that
they just don't seem to go here that was
that was
>> because it Yeah. So that that's I think
exactly the point I'm making that that
one does not derive it from this update
formula except in to say that if um so
if we were dealing with a convergence of
Q of pi P of pi then it would depend
upon the form of P of pi. And if P of pi
is defined in such a way that we expect
the actions we take to minimize expected
free energy or or to be sort of
inversely monotonically proportional to
expected free energy then it emerges
directly from this biting.
>> No
prior the objection I was making. Okay.
>> Uh so I have to toggle between two
slides. So uh so here
we both agree this is in my reading the
E E vector. Okay the prior unhabits.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. This is the variational free
energy of a policy
calculated with the uh observations up
to the present moment. And this term in
equation B.9 is expected free energy.
And
>> that's the point where that's the point
where that's not true anymore.
>> So from the perspective of the way this
equation would be expressed in the
active inference book
um both the f of the the less than or
equal to t and the f of greater than t
are both included as a single f term.
the expected free energy would actually
be part of the log p of pi.
>> Oh okay. But um
okay so there are two ways you can um
implement this type of thing. You can
take it that pi is a or the p of pi is
um a prior distribution on
um policies.
Okay. I think the term habit might be
used. Okay. And then that can be updated
at every time at every time step.
>> Yes. So you can use the Q at calculated
at time t as a prior at time t + one.
Yes,
>> I sort of left this vague in in
formulating this uh as to whether that
uh prior in policies was something that
was given in advance and never changed
or
uh was susceptible to being changed as
uh observations were accumulated. So it
could be implemented either way. So
again,
>> I think I think I mean I I I would have
to I would have to
think in terms of
>> Sorry. Do you do you finish what you're
saying?
>> No, I I I I'm winging it at this point.
I I I would have to think about it more
carefully if there is an issue here.
>> Yes. So I'm not saying there's an issue
with how you formulated it and what you
what you've written is perfectly
reasonable for a sort of passive
observer. um who or or an observer that
behaves in a purely habitual way of
working out what I'm going to do next.
The that the um and part of that is
taking evidence from um what what I've
done so far and and that's um what the
the sort of ferms here are contributing.
They're contributing a an element of uh
the evidence in favor of this policy
from the things I've already done in the
past. Um the
the the big difference is that the the
assumption that one can derive the
expected free energy from this is not
correct. Uh and that is not what it's
used for. The expected free energy is
not something that's used to derive an
update scheme. It is a way of defining
P of pi um which may have a habitual
component and may also have a component
from the expected free energy. So one
could write it as if you wanted a
habitual component you could do that P
of pi is a sort of E term as you've said
multiplied by the exponent of the
negative expected free energy but that
is a definition of a prior it it is not
a a derived prior
>> okay I I'll take your word for it I I
may have misread the um the the
presentation and misunderstood some um
basic point Yeah.
>> Well, I I think it it's a point that
comes back a lot and you know, I I
completely understand why that's a it's
an unusual point to get one's head
around that if we're so used to seeing
an expected free energy or a kale
divergence as being the objective
function to be optimized. Um it it feels
strange to use it as a way of of
defining a pri and it's something that
doesn't happen in most of basin infants
because the idea of defining a prior
based upon a function that is itself a
functional of uh of our current beliefs
and current posteriors feels like a very
strange thing to do. But this is one of
the the things at the heart of active
inference that really makes it differ
from things like reinforcement learning.
It's the idea that the that a good
policy or a good thing to do is not
defined just in terms of what I might
get at the end, but actually in terms of
our beliefs and how those beliefs might
be optimized over time.
Um and and so what you've written down
is not wrong at all in the sense of um
in deriving a way of coming up with a
good predictive distribution based upon
some alternative trajectories I might be
on perhaps with a prior bias for
thinking I might be more likely on this
trajectory than this one. But what it
doesn't get at is a form of agency that
that uh that sort of updates based upon
either explicit goals or or in terms of
um in terms of curiosity and belief
updating to minimize uncertainty and to
resolve uncertainty about the world
around us. And I think that's the point
I was I was going to come back to about
the the difference between these
different approaches. Um
and
you can see that in in in that there is
you know what what it comes back exactly
to our point about convergence doesn't
it that if the uh effective objective
function that you end up with is defined
as just the kale divergence between two
um between a prior belief about how
things will play out and my beliefs
about how things will play out. then one
converges to a point where the H&M
matches uh my beliefs about how things
will play.
Um and so there is a convergence there.
Whereas if one is actively selecting
alternative trajectories based upon how
they will optimize my beliefs in the
future, that's a very different sort of
of of model, something that has a lot
more autonomy to it.
Let me let me ask you um the the um
at least the the basic implicit
assumption that I'm making is that uh
all of the um the agents beliefs about
the world and uh it's uh the actions
open to it and the policies and so on
can be encoded in a single HM in
princip. principle
assuming a sufficiently rich structure
and if if that if that encoding is done
then uh there is no explicit role played
by um policies.
>> Yes, I noticed that in in in your paper
as well. Um, and I think that's a good
summary of of why that's different to
sort of more conventional act of
inference that that it this is not about
policies. This is not about planning.
Uh, this is about predicting the future.
>> I I I actually agree with that last
statement that you made unreserveably.
So I I am uh asking then uh if um
holding uh actions and policies into
states is somehow an impediment
to uh making predictions about the
future.
>> It depends how I model myself and the
way I will impact the observations I
might see in the future.
Those are actions, right? Those are
actions. And if we in the basic picture,
actions are just transition probability
matrices on a state space.
>> Yes. But how do I select one action over
another? And
>> you have an well I'm proposing uh a
particular objective function
that you see that you're seeking to
optimize.
>> Yes. Um and the the way in which this
objective function works as you can see
in this in this is exactly the same as
it would work for any of the states as
well that I don't control.
Yes indeed I I I I agree that this this
is a fascinating question you know about
the difference between reflexive
actions
um and if you like deliberate actions if
they somehow require
uh different modeling I I I'm inclined
to think that they don't but that's who
who am I to
because I'm coming at this as as an
outsider. But if they don't require
separate modeling, then I believe that
the framework I've presented is
adequate.
>> Yes, I think on on that assumption, you
know, with that caveat of saying
predicting a a sort of passive playing
out of of the world and of of the
actions I can take in it, if there is no
difference between those things, then I
completely agree. It's
>> well, is it Okay. If you could point me
to a paper where this uh issue is uh
trashed out, I I would be very keen to u
to read it.
>> When you say this issue, you you mean
>> maybe whether
uh there is a fundamental difference
between
uh reflexive actions. Okay. And so each
has to infer what he's doing. and um
deliberate actions which uh involve uh
offline some sort of distance from um
what's going on where the where the
where that is causally
uh um efficacious. Uh
>> yeah.
>> Yes. And and you know I think this is
actually one of those really interesting
connections again back to what we were
saying about the difference between the
way a lot of the continuous space state
space models work and the way in which a
lot of the the uh discrete omdp like
models are are formulated. Um, and the
I guess the key thing in a lot of the
way the continuous models are and this
isn't necessarily because they're
continuous, but that but they match the
same sort of principles that you've been
describing in that there is no need to
explicitly model myself or or or maybe I
I might model the position of my limb
for instance and predict where I might
see it at some point in time. Um but
what I don't have to model necessarily
is uh how I will make decisions, how I
will plan. There's no sort of
self-modeling involved in it. But as
soon as you say how the world evolves
depends upon which decisions I make, one
needs to have prior about which decision
they are likely to make given a set of
beliefs that they would have at that
point in time. And it's only by
incorporating that that you can then
predict futures that that that we
ourselves influence and create.
So that's that's the distinction. It it
and in terms of the modeling, you know,
you can still use exactly the same
machinery you've described, but you need
to change the prior. So again, it comes
back to this point that the model is
central the general.
>> Yeah. The question in my mind is whether
everything can be encoded
in the HM.
>> Well,
I think it you know you you can
certainly write down an HMM in which
there are some states that are states
and there are some states that are
policies.
>> Well,
and and I think that's what you're
describing. But the question is,
>> is there something meaningfully distinct
between those two different kinds of
entity?
>> That's what that's what I'm sort of
pushing back against. Okay. I I I I'm
aware of this issue and um I I find it
fascinating and I'm actually just
putting my foot down and saying
>> yeah,
>> this is not a real problem. There's a
sense in which in the total joint
distribution of let's say agent and
niche again it is great to have an
evenhanded
approach to those variables. At the same
time it's like the difference between
external context shifts which are
changes in potentially causal external
influences
that there are uncertainty profiles
over. And then there's the kind of
internal context shifts or actions and
the agent in the specification and the
implementation. You have that agent
doing actual agencyoriented policy
search over what I could do. I could
move my eyes there. I could look here
and that has all these implications for
precision and salience. Whereas you
still could have uncertainty profiles
and transition matrices over like I'm a
marionette and my arm will be moved
there by this external force. But that
would be represented with an uncertainty
over those those changes in the world
which are not under one's own agency
versus ones that are. And it's like you
need to do policy inference for the true
I could do that whereas this could
happen to me you could just be uncertain
about like whether it rains or not.
Well, let me let me give the
counterargument, okay, which which would
say that um
the
uh the agent's job is to predict its
actions and the way it predicts its
actions is by predicting its
sensations. It's interceptive and auton
or whatever proprioceptive
uh sensations and then fulfilling those
uh predictions because on sufficiently
short uh time scales
those predictions can be fulfilled
uh reflexively
motor reflexes and and autonomic
reflexes.
So if the agent can successfully predict
its future sensations, successfully
predict them, okay, then it can fulfill
them
um unconsciously as it were. I mean
without without having to so that's why
I think that the reflex of picture is
sufficient. Yes, there is this sort of
like ultimate witness
view where everything including what
might be seen as intentional or even
internally perceived as intentional is
also like a willless unfolding.
That's I I guess I'm I I am the plastic
determinist at heart and um
>> that's that's how that's how I see
nature including human nature and I see
a lot of um push back against that in
the act of inference literature or a lot
of um shall we say humanists who who
don't like this uh purely mechanical
um statistical physical account of of
human behavior, but it it it works for
me.
>> Well, I think they are perhaps slightly
different distinctions.
I I would argue that that sort of
conventional accounts of active
inference don't necessarily appeal to
anything other than statistical and
physical. Well, well, I mean there is
the field has generated so much interest
uh in the humanities. Okay. that um
>> and that's because I think uh humanists
see a bridge between um
well
car's uh worldview and and their own
but my reading of Christian is that it
is uh deeply mechanistic and um
ultimately
reflexive.
I think
>> yes and I you know I agree with you the
reflexive aspect is incredibly important
and I think a part of all active
inference formulations
um the the idea of it being of just
having the and and you know the at the
sort of lowest level of the model where
we interface with sensory data I think
that is always the assumption that
simply to fulfill predictions and what
you've described today is is precisely
the philosophy and approach that
underlies the the quite traditional
continuous state space approaches to
active inference.
>> And there is no reason why one can't
apply exactly those same approaches
equally validly to to discrete state
spaces. Um so you know the the approach
you you you've outlined is completely
reasonable. Um but it addresses a very
different question and problem to that
addressed by expected free energy. So
it's a different domain. It's a it's a
different category of thing. The
expected free energy is a way of saying
if I were to predict what I'm going to
do next, knowing the beliefs I hold now,
how would I weight those alternative
actions, those alternative trajectories,
those alternative choices in relation to
the beliefs I have now. And that comes
down to a question of prior.
It's a question of um how do I believe I
would behave in this situation? And one
can't do that with a prior that is just
a fixed form. I always do this in this
situation which is is what you're
describing in terms of
>> well I I I think we we we are now um
circling the same u problem
you know as I see it the problem is
uh is it possible to
um formulate a single generative model
such as HMN which encodes
all of uh an agent 's
uh beliefs um actions, policies
uh its whole world cannot be
encapsulated
in a single HM and if it can then the
calculations with that HMM will be just
mechanistic.
>> Yes,
>> that's the question. Uh, of course I
don't. Yeah.
>> And and I think the point I'm making is
that that your answer is a perfectly
reasonable answer, but you're addressing
a different question to what is expected
free energy for. So you could have
written this paper and this talk without
reference to expected free energy.
>> Oh, that's well that's interesting.
>> And I would have had very few very few
uh points of contention.
>> Oh, okay. Well, I I would certainly
certainly be uh curious to
uh to hear of any other, you know,
judgments
u that other people might um have on on
that uh on that particular issue. Um
yeah, it could be that I've completely
misunderstood it because I've just come
as a complete outsider and um well, if I
was doing it, then this is how I would
do it. And uh that was what prompted me
to prepare for it.
>> Not not about being an insider or
outsider. This is a right of passage.
This is something that that sort of many
people go through.
I think is
>> okay.
>> Okay. That's um I think maybe we should
uh we should conclude on that now for
>> Yeah. It it is an evergreen genre. first
principles from first principles and all
of our journeys and our abilities as
time goes forward to integrate these
formalisms and come to more and more
consolidated
streamlined representations of them.
It's just the beginning of that day. So
Patrick, thank you for the paper and I
hope it spurs correspondence and
dialogue. And Thomas, thank you for the
textbook and all the work and these
comments here today.
Thank you. Thank you. It was my
pleasure. I I enjoyed the discussion
very much.
>> All right. Bye.
>> Okay.
Okay.
Thank you. See you later.